Postdoctoral Scholar School of Computer Science & Engineering University of Washington

- https://shagunjhaver.com
- (972) 400-1096

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research uses mixed-methods techniques to study how large-scale online social systems work, where they fail, and how to improve them. My current research focus is on building end-users tools to protect against online harassment, evaluating the effects of banning or quarantining Reddit communities, and analyzing the moderation mechanisms that curate Facebook ads.

Topics: Social Computing, Human-Computer Interaction, Content Moderation, Online Harassment, Social Media Content Analysis, Quantitative & Qualitative Data Analysis

EDUCATION

GEORGIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY, Atlanta, GA USA

Ph.D., Computer Science

Dissertation: Identifying Opportunities to Improve Content Moderation

Advisors: Amy Bruckman and Eric Gilbert

Committee: Scott Counts, Neha Kumar, Keith Edwards

University of Texas at Dallas, Richardson, TX USA

M.S., Computer Science

Thesis: Large Scale Data Mining with Applications in Social Computing

Advisor: Latifur Khan

INDIAN INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY BOMBAY, Mumbai, India

B.Tech., Electrical Engineering

Aug 2006 - May 2010

Aug 2012 - Dec 2014

Aug 2015 – May 2020

GPA: 4.0/4.0

AWARDS AND RECOGNITION

- Best Paper Award, CSCW (2019)
- Best Paper Honorable Mention Award, CSCW (2019)
- Featured in Editor's Spotlight, TOCHI (2018)
- Best Paper Award, ICWSM (2016)

PUBLICATIONS

PEER-REVIEWED JOURNAL AND CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

[11] **Shagun Jhaver**, Amy Bruckman, and Eric Gilbert. (2019). "Does Transparency in Moderation Really Matter?: User Behavior After Content Removal Explanations on Reddit." In *Proceedings of the ACM Human-Computer Interaction (CSCW 2019)*.

Best Paper Award

[10] **Shagun Jhaver**, Scott Appling, Eric Gilbert, and Amy Bruckman. (2019). ""Did You Suspect the Post Would be Removed?": User Reactions to Content Removals on Reddit." In *Proceedings of the ACM Human-Computer Interaction (CSCW 2019)*.

Best Paper Honorable Mention Award

- [9] Maya Holikatti, **Shagun Jhaver**, and Neha Kumar. (2019). "Learning to Airbnb by Engaging in Online Communities of Practice." In *Proceedings of the ACM Human-Computer Interaction (CSCW* 2019).
- [8] **Shagun Jhaver**, Justin Cranshaw, Scott Counts. (2019). "Measuring Professional Skill Development in U.S. Cities Using Internet Search Queries." In *Proceedings of the 13th International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM 2019)*.
- [7] **Shagun Jhaver**, Iris Birman, Eric Gilbert, Amy Bruckman. (2019). "Human-Machine Collaboration for Content Regulation: The Case of Reddit Automoderator." *ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI)*.
- [6] **Shagun Jhaver**, Yoni Karpfen, and Judd Antin. (2018). "Algorithmic Anxiety and Coping Strategies of Airbnb Hosts." In *Proceedings of the 35th Annual ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2018)*.
- [5] **Shagun Jhaver**, Sucheta Ghoshal, Amy Bruckman and Eric Gilbert. (2018). "Online Harassment and Content Moderation: The Case of Blocklists." *ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI)*.

Featured in Editor's Spotlight

- [4] Eshwar Chandrasekharan, Mattia Samory, **Shagun Jhaver**, Hunter Charvat, Amy Bruckman, Cliff Lampe, Jacob Eisenstein and Eric Gilbert. (2018). "The Internet's Hidden Rules: An Empirical Study of Reddit Norm Violations at Micro, Meso, and Macro Scales." In *Proceedings of the ACM Human-Computer Interaction Article* 32 (CSCW 2018).
- [3] **Shagun Jhaver**, Larry Chan, and Amy Bruckman. (2018). "The View from the Other Side: The Border Between Controversial Speech and Harassment on Kotaku in Action." *First Monday*.
- [2] Munmun De Choudhury, **Shagun Jhaver**, Benjamin Sugar, and Ingmar Webar. (2016). "Social Media Participation in an Activist Movement for Racial Equality." In *Proceedings of the 10th International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM 2016)*. **Best Paper Award**
- [1] **Shagun Jhaver**, Latifur Khan, and Bhavani Thuraisingham. (2014). "Calculating Edit Distance for Large Sets of String Pairs using MapReduce." In *Proceedings of the ASE International Conference on Big Data 2014*.

Workshops Organized (Peer Reviewed)

[1] Charles Kiene, **Shagun Jhaver**, Eshwar Chandrasekharan, Bryan Dosono, Brianna Dym, Sarah Gilbert, Aaron Jiang, Kat Lo, Joseph Seering, Kenny Shores, and D. Yvette Wohn. "Volunteer Work: Mapping the Future of Moderation Research." *In ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW 2019).*

Posters (Peer Reviewed)

[1] **Shagun Jhaver**, Larry Chan, and Sandeep Soni. "PostScholar: Surfacing Social Signals in Google Scholar Search." *In Proceedings of the 19th ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing Companion (CSCW 2016).*

Workshop Proceedings (Lightly Peer Reviewed)

[2] **Shagun Jhaver**. "Leveraging Focus Theory of Normative Conduct to Shape User Behavior." *Managing and Designing for Norms in Online Communities* Workshop. *In Proceedings of the 13th International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM 2019)*.

[1] **Shagun Jhaver**. "Designing 'Understanding Mechanisms' to Fight Online Harassment." *Understanding Bad Actors Online* Workshop. *In Proceedings of the 35th Annual ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems* (CHI 2018).

TECHNICAL REPORTS AND THESES

- [2] **Shagun Jhaver**, Pranil Vora, and Amy Bruckman. (2017). "Designing for Civil Conversations: Lessons Learned from ChangeMyView." *GVU Technical Report*.
- [1] **Shagun Jhaver**. (2014). "Large Scale Data Mining with Applications in Social Computing." Master's Thesis, University of Texas at Dallas.

GRANTS

"Evaluating the Effectiveness of Deplatforming as a Moderation Strategy"
 Facebook

Shagun Jhaver, Christian Boylston, Amy Bruckman, Diyi Yang

Amount: \$99,708 Duration: 9 months

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- School of Interactive Computing, Georgia Institute of Technology

 I have used computational techniques, surveys, interviews and participant observations to understand key aspects of sociotechnical systems, such as how content moderation happens on social media websites, and how users perceive and react to different moderation mechanisms.
- Department of Computer Science, University of Texas at Dallas
 I developed a framework to perform setwise classification on streaming data by designing an ensemble of models that addressed the challenges of concept drift, concept evolution, and storage limitations. I used this framework to conduct real-time sentiment analyses of Twitter posts.

RESEARCH INTERNSHIPS

- Microsoft Research, Seattle, WA USA
 With Scott Counts and Justin Cranshaw Social Computing Group

 Studied the role of self-directed skill development on economic growth across all US cities using large-scale search query data.
- Airbnb, Inc., San Francisco, CA USA
 With Judd Antin Homes 2.0 Team

 Investigated the impact of algorithmic evaluation on users and their work practices in the context of sharing economy platforms.
- Brown University, Providence, RI USA
 Data Management Research Group
 Helped build a new system for big data analytics and performed in-memory computations on large clusters in a fault-tolerant manner.

• INRIA Research Centre, Paris-Rocquencourt, France Contraintes Research team May 2009 – July 2009

Developed mathematical models to analyze biomolecular networks using MATLAB.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

 Amazon.com, Inc., Seattle, WA USA Vendor Express Team Mar 2015 – July 2015

Developed support for mobile users on the Vendor Express platform, created internal tools for faster support case management, and implemented Vendor Express for Germany and Japan.

• Future Group, Mumbai, India

Jan 2011 – Jun 2012

Head of the Analytics and Business Intelligence Team. Conceptualized and implemented *Order Life-cycle Management*, a system to process and manage orders. Developed a website for sellers to track orders, sales summary, and product reviews.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

HEAD TEACHING ASSISTANT, GEORGIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY

• CS 4863: Computers, Society, and Professionalism

Fall 2019

- Assisting Prof. Amy Bruckman with developing this new course.
- **Instructing** a section of the course.
- CS 3600: Intro. to Artificial Intelligence

Spring 2018

- Managed and mentored other Teaching Assistants.
- Facilitated proctoring and grading of exams.

TEACHING ASSISTANT, GEORGIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY

• CS 3600: Intro. to Artificial Intelligence	Summer 2019
CS 4001: Computing & Society	Fall 2018
CS 4001: Computing & Society	Fall 2017
CS 3600: Intro. to Artificial Intelligence	Spring 2017
CS 4001: Computing & Society	Fall 2016
CS 3600: Intro. to Artificial Intelligence	Spring 2016

GUEST LECTURER

• CS 6470, "Deviant Behavior," Georgia Tech	Spring 2019
• CS 6470, "Content Moderation," Georgia Tech	Spring 2019
 CS 4001, "Online Harassment & Content Moderation," Georgia Tech 	Fall 2018
• CS 4001, "Academic Urban Legends," Georgia Tech	Fall 2017

MATH AND PHYSICS TUTOR

Student Success Center, University of Texas at Dallas

Jan - Oct 2013

- Assisted students of all levels on various Math and Physics university courses.
- Conducted exam reviews.

SERVICE & MENTORING

REVIEWING

• CHI 2017-2020.

- CSCW 2018-20.
- GROUP 2020.
- First Monday.
- Big Data & Society.
- ACL Workshop on Abusive Language Online (ALW3).

STUDENT MENTORING

- Maya Holikatti B.S. Computer Science: Learning Mechanisms of Airbnb Hosts
- Christian J Boylston B.S. Computer Science: Effects of Deplatforming on Twitter
- Josiah Mangiameli M.S. Human Computer Interaction: User Reactions to Content Removals on Reddit
- Kevin Tang B.S. Game and Interactive Media Design: Removal Explanations on Reddit
- Iris Birman B.S. Computer Science: Moderation of Reddit Communities
- Francisco A Zampieri B.S. Computer Science: Effects of Community Response on User Behavior
- Pranil Vora B.S. Computer Science: Design Mechanisms of the ChangeMyView Subreddit
- Benjamin Sugar M.S. Digital Media: Social Media Participation in the Black Lives Matter Movement

SELECTED PRESS COVERAGE

- MIT Technology Review, Reddit's automoderator is the future of the internet, and deeply imperfect. (2019)
- New Scientist, Explaining why Reddit posts are removed helps people comply with rules. (2019)
- Forbes, Why Republicans Weren't The Only Ones Shadow Banned On Twitter. (2018)
- Washington Post, Here's proof that not everything was terrible on the Internet in 2017. (2017)
- Al Jazeera, Black Lives Matter: The social media behind a movement. (2016)
- Futurity, Tweets shift tone before Black Lives Matter protests. (2016)

Last updated: September 6, 2020 https://shagunjhaver.com